Almira Sadykova-DuMond

Largo, MD, 20774 almira.sdumond@gmail.com

Data Scientist/Language Engineer

github.com/sadykova linkedin.com/in/almira-sadykova

Creative, multilingual, team-oriented Data Scientist seeking a position as a Data Scientist/Language Engineer in technology industry. Passionate and highly motivated, with six years of experience in statistical analysis, dataset engineering, and research. Looking to apply statistical and technical skills to generate and visualize insights from natural language databases.

SKILLS

General Research, Data Cleaning, Querying and Managing Data, Data Visualization, Data Geocoding, Machine

Learning, Statistical Analysis

Operating Systems Windows, Linux

Programming Languages Python (NumPy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-learn, SpaCy, NLTK), R (tidyr, dplyr, ggplot2, leaflet,

shiny, caret), JavaScript

Other Programming and

Software Skills

SQL, HTML & CSS, LaTeX, Microsoft Office, STATA, Git, LexisNexis, VS Code, Jupyter Notebook, Zoom

Language Skills English (Fluent), Kazakh (Native), Russian (Native level proficiency), Turkish (Fluent), Arabic (Beginner)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Graduate Assistant August 2018 — Present

Binghamton University (SUNY)

Binghamton, NY

- Created an automated events extractor using Python's SpaCy package to parse text and to machine code repression events from news articles in LexisNexis using a rule-based matching
- Used Python's Pygooglenews package to scrape Google News to gather information pertaining to protest and repression events
- Extracted protest locations from unstructured text using Natural Language Toolkit (NLTK) package in Python for CIA-sponsored Mass Mobilization Project
- Geocoded protest locations using Python's GeoPy package
- Created protest location maps and published them as an interactive web application using R's leaflet and shiny packages
- Updated data visualizations on Mass Mobilizations project's website using HTML and CSS
- Taught an upper-level undergraduate class on visualizing political violence data employing Shiny package in R (Winter 2022, Binghamton University)
- Gathering information on counterterrorism curfews in the Middle East using LexisNexis and developing theoretical framework that can be used to assess potential direct and indirect effects of curfew impositions for ongoing dissertation project
- Collected and catalogued data on states' ratification of counterterrorism treaties and states' non-negotiation policies with terrorists to evaluate their effects on terrorist activity using regression analysis

Teaching and Research Assistant

July 2016 — July 2018

Nazarbayev University, Graduate School of Public Policy

Nur-Sultan, KZ

- Served as instructor of record for recitation sections of 25-60 students focusing on statistical concepts and statistical software (e.g. STATA, Excel)
- Proctored and graded examinations for introductory statistical courses
- · Calculated student grades using Moodle software for submission to university's registrar office
- Coded large-N survey data using Excel for university faculty

Public Relations Manager

Kazakhtelecom JSC

July 2012 — April 2014

Nur-Sultan, KZ

- Prepared and organized external communications and press releases for senior executives
- Oversaw large scale advertising budget and procurement of contracts with regional news outlets
- Communicated directly with consumers using social media presence to ensure customer satisfaction

TranslatorAkgun Software
Suly 2010 — July 2012
Nur-Sultan, KZ

- Performed software localization of health information systems from Turkish to Kazakh and Russian languages for local hospitals
- Conducted written and oral translations for technical documents and business executive meetings
- · Updated company marketing materials through translation and redevelopment for Kazakhstani consumers

EDUCATION

Degrees

Doctor Of Philosophy, Political Science, Binghamton University, State University of New YorkAugust 2018-PresentMaster of Arts, Political Science, Binghamton University, State University of New YorkDecember 2019Master of Arts, Political Science, Nazarbayev University (Nur-Sultan, KZ)May 2016Bachelor of Arts, Journalism, L.N. Gumilyov Eurasian National University (Nur-Sultan, KZ)May 2012

Certificates

Software Development Bootcamp, Code The DreamJuly 2022-PresentApplied Machine Learning in Social Science Research , ICPSR (Ann Arbor, MI)July 2020Introduction to R, ICPSR (Ann Arbor, MI)July 2020Regression Analysis, National University of Singapore (Singapore)July 2015